<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="bpmn2">
  
  <title>BPMN 2.0</title>
  
  <section id="whatIsBpmn">
    
    <title>What is BPMN 2.0?</title>
    
    <para>
			The Business Process Modeling Notation (BPMN) is a standard for the
			graphical notation of business process models. The standard is
			maitained by the Object Management Group (OMG).
		</para>
		<para>	
			Basically, the BPMN specification defines how a task must look like, which constructs can
			be connected to each other, etc. in a meaning that cannot be
			misinterpreted.
		</para>
    <para>
	    Earlier versions of the standard (&lt;= version 1.2) are limited to the modeling
			only, aiming at a common understanding between all stakeholders
			involved in documenting, discussing and implementing business
			processes. The BPMN standard has proven itself, as many modeling tools
			on the market today use the symbols and constructs specified in the
			BPMN standard. In fact, the current JPDL designer also uses BPMN
			symbols.
		</para>
    <para>
		  Version 2.0 of the BPMN specification, which is currently in finalization phase and is
			scheduled to be finished soon, allows to add precise technical
			details to the shapes and symbols available in BPMN and at the same
			time specify what the execution semantics of BPMN 'elements' are. By
			using an XML language to specify the executable semantics of a business
			process, the BPMN specification has evolved into a language for
			business processes that can be executed on any BPMN2 compliant process
			engine - while still having the powerful graphical notation.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="historyAndGodl">
  
    <title>History and goal</title>
    
    <para>
			The jBPM BPMN2 implementation was started in close collaboration with the
			community in augustus 2009 after releasing jBPM 4.0. 
			Later, it was decided that the first release (ie documented/QA'd) to
			incorporate parts of the BPMN2 spec would be jBPM 4.3.
		</para>
    <para>
			The goal of this effort is to build a <emphasis role="bold">native BPMN2 runtime engine </emphasis>
			(or better said implementing 'BPMN2 exectuable') leveraging the Process
			Virtual Machine (PVM).
			Do note that the primary focus of this release is native executability,
			not the graphical notation - but we recognize its importance for
			further releases. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">
      Users who are already familiar with jBPM will find that
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>the configuration mechanism remains unchanged</listitem>
        <listitem>the API is the same or very similar to the existing one</listitem>
        <listitem>testing BPMN2 process still can be done with regular Java testing frameworks</listitem>
        <listitem>the database schema remains unchanged</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </emphasis>
      So in general, our main goal is to keep everything that was good about jBPM, and enhance
      it with a standards based process language.
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
  <section id="jpdlVsBpmn2" >
  
    <title>JPDL vs BPMN 2.0</title>
		
		<para>
			One of the first questions that might, rightfully, come to mind is why
			BPMN2 is being implemented while there is jPDL. Both are languages
			have as goal to define executable business processes. From a high-level
			technical point of view, both languages are equivalent. The main
			distinction is that BPMN2 is as vendor-neutral as you can have with
			standards, while JPDL has always been tied to jBPM (although some might
			argue that a vendor lock-in for an open-source process language such as
			JPDL is less a lock-in than with closed-source products).
		</para>
    <para>
			Within jBPM, both language implementations are built on top of the jBPM
			Process Virtual Machine (PVM). This means that both languages share a
			common foundation (persistence, transactions, configuration, but also
			basic process constructs, etc.). As a result, optimizations to the core
			of jBPM often benefits both languages. Leveraging the PVM, the BPMN2
			implementation is built upon a foundation that has already proven
			itself in the past and has a large end-user community.
		</para>
    <para>
		  When evaluating the languages and comparing them which each other however,
			following points must be taken into consideration:
		  <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>BPMN2 is based on a standard accepted by the BPM industry.</listitem>
        <listitem>BPMN2 is implementation-unaware. The downside of this is that
		      integrating with Java technology will always be easier with JPDL. So,
		      from a Java developer's perspective JPDL is simpler and feels more
		      natural (some of the 'layers' of BPEL/WSDL are in BPMN as well).</listitem>
        <listitem>A focus of JPDL is XML readability. BPMN2 processes will still be
		      readable to a certain level, but tooling or a more detailed knowledge
		      of the spec will definitely be required to achieve the same level of
		      productivity.</listitem>
        <listitem>Java developers who are super-fast in JPDL since they know the JPDL
		      language by heart, will find the use of tools sometimes bothersome and
		      the language itself overly complicated.</listitem>
        <listitem>BPMN2 contains a large set of constructs described in the
		      specification. However, the "binding" of interfaces to code is left
		      open in the spec (comparable with XPDL), even if WDSL is often considered the
		      default. This means that a process portability can be lost when porting
		      the process to an engine that doesn't support the same binding
		      mechanism. Calling Java classes for example is already going to be such
		      a jBPM specific binding.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
		</para>
    <para>
			It is natural to the political level of BPMN2 specification process to go
			rather slow. JPDL on the other hand will be able to incorporate changes
			faster, integrate with new technologies when they are released and
			evolve generally at a quicker pace compared to BPMN2.
		
			Of course, since both are built on top of the same PVM, it is only
			logical that additions to JPDL can be ported to BPMN2 as an extension
			without much hassle.
	</para>
  
  </section>
  
  <section id="Bpmn2Execution" >
  
    <title>Bpmn 2.0 execution</title>

    <para>
			The BPMN2 specification defines a very rich language for modeling and
			executing business processes. However, this also means that it is quite
			hard to get an overview of what's possible with BPMN2. To simplify this
			situation, we've decided to categorize the BPMN2 constructs into three
			'levels'. The separation itself is primarily based on the book 'BPMN
			method and Style' by Bruce Silver (<ulink url="http://www.bpmnstyle.com/">http://www.bpmnstyle.com/</ulink>), the
			training material of Dr. Jim Arlow
			(<ulink url="http://www.slideshare.net/jimarlow/introductiontobpmn005">http://www.slideshare.net/jimarlow/introductiontobpmn005</ulink>), 
			'How much BPMN do you need'
			(<ulink url="http://www.bpm-research.com/2008/03/03/how-much-bpmn-do-you-need/">http://www.bpm-research.com/2008/03/03/how-much-bpmn-do-you-need/</ulink>),
			and also our own experience.
		</para>
		<para>
			We define three categories of BPMN2 constructs:
		  <itemizedlist>
		    <listitem><emphasis role="bold">Basic</emphasis>: constructs in this category are 
		      straight-forward and easy to grasp. Constructs in this category can be used to 
		      model simple business processes.</listitem>
		    <listitem><emphasis role="bold">Advanced</emphasis>: contains more powerful or 
		      expressive constructs, but this comes with higher modeling and execution semantics 
		      learning curve. The majority of business processes are implementable with constructs from this
		      and the previous category.</listitem>
		    <listitem><emphasis role="bold">Complex</emphasis>: constructs in this category are 
		      used in specific and/or rare cases, or their semantics are difficult to understand.</listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
  </section>  
    
  <section id="bpmn2Config">
    
    <title>Configuration</title>
      
    <para>
      Enabling BPMN 2.0 in your application is extremely simple: just add the following line
      to the <emphasis role="bold">jbpm.cfg.xml</emphasis> file.
      <programlisting>
&lt;import resource=&quot;jbpm.bpmn.cfg.xml&quot; /&gt;        
      </programlisting>
      This import will enable BPMN 2.0 process deployment by installing a BPMN 2.0 deployer
      in the Process Engine. Do note that a Process Engine can cope with both JPDL and BPMN 2.0
      processes. This means that in your application, some processes can be JPDL and others
      can be BPMN 2.0.
    </para>
      
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Process definitions are distinguished by the process engine
      based on the extension of the definition file. For BPMN 2.0, use the *.bpmn.xml extension
      (where JPDL is having the *.jpdl.xml extension).</emphasis>
    </para>
    
  </section>
    
  <section id="bpmn2Examples">
    
    <title>Examples</title>
    
    <para>
      The examples that are shipped with the distribution also contain examples for every 
      construct that is discussed in the following sections. Look for example BPMN 2.0
      processes and test cases in the <emphasis role="bold">org.jbpm.examples.bpmn.* package
      </emphasis>.
    </para>
      
    <para>
      See the userguide, chapter 2 (Installation), for a walktough on how to import the examples.
      Look for the section <emphasis role="bold">'Importing the Examples'</emphasis>.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="definitionsAndProcess">
  
     <title>Process root element</title>
     
     <para>
      The root of an BPMN 2.0 XML process is the <emphasis role="bold">definitions</emphasis> 
      elements. As the name states, the subelements will contain the actual definitions of
      the business process(es). Every <emphasis role="bold">process</emphasis> child
      will be able to have an <emphasis role="bold">id (required)</emphasis> and
      <emphasis role="bold">name (optional)</emphasis>. An empty business process in BPMN 2.0
      looks as follows. Also note that it is handy to have the BPMN2.xsd on the classpath, to
      enable XML completion.
      <programlisting>
&lt;definitions id=&quot;myProcesses&quot;
  xmlns:xsi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance&quot;
  xsi:schemaLocation=&quot;http://schema.omg.org/spec/BPMN/2.0 BPMN20.xsd&quot;
  xmlns=&quot;http://schema.omg.org/spec/BPMN/2.0&quot; 
  typeLanguage=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema&quot;
  expressionLanguage=&quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/XPath&quot; 
  targetNamespace=&quot;http://jbpm.org/example/bpmn2&quot;&gt;

  &lt;process id=&quot;My business processs&quot; name=&quot;myBusinessProcess&quot;&gt; 
  
      ...
      
  &lt;/process&gt;
&lt;definitions&gt;     
      </programlisting>
      If a name is defined for the process element, it is be used as <emphasis role="bold">key</emphasis>
      for that process (ie. starting a process can be done by calling executionService.startProcessInstanceByKey("myBusinessProcess").
      If no name is defined, the id will be used as key. So having only an id defined, will allow
      to start a process instance using that id. So basically, name and key are of equivalent 
      in usage, for example to search process definitions. Note that for a key the same rules apply as with
      JPDL: whitespace and non alpha-numeric characters are replaced by an underscore.
     </para>
  
  </section>
    
  <section id="basicConstructs">
    
    <title>Basic constructs</title>
      
    <section id="basicConstructsEvents">
      
      <title>Events</title>
        
      <para>
        Together with activitites and gateways, events are used in practically every business process.
        Events allow process modelers to describe business processes in a very natural way, such as
        <emphasis>'This process starts when I receive a customer order'</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>'If the task is not finished in 2 days, terminate the process'</emphasis>
        or <emphasis>'When I receive a cancel e-mail when the process is running,
        handle the e-mail using this sub-process'</emphasis>. Notice that typical businesses
        always work in a very event-driven way. People are not hard-coded sequential creatures,
        but they tend to react on things that happen in their environment (ie. events).
        In the BPMN specification, a great number of event types are described, to cover the
        range of possible things that might occur in context of a business.  
      </para>
    
    </section>  
        
    <section id="noneStartEvent">
        
      <title>Event: None start event</title>
          
      <para>
        A start event indicates the start of process (or a subprocess). Graphically, it is visualized
        as a circle with (possibly) a small icon inside. The icon specifies the actual type of event 
        that will trigger the process instance creation.
      </para>
           
      <para>
        The 'none start event' is drawn as a circle without an icon inside, which means that the
        trigger is unknown or unspecified. The start activity of JPDL basically has the same
        semantics. Process instances whose process definition has a 'none start event' are 
        created using the typical API calls on the <emphasis role="bold">executionService</emphasis>.
       </para>
          
       <para>
         A none start event is defined as follows. An id is required, a name is optional.
         <programlisting>
&lt;startEvent id=&quot;start&quot;  name=&quot;myStart&quot; /&gt;            
          </programlisting>
       </para>
        
    </section>

    <section id="noneEndEvent">

		  <title>Event: None end event</title>

		  <para>
			  An end event indicates the end of an execution path in a process
			  instance. Graphically,
			  it is visualized as a circle with a thick border with (possibly) a
			  small icon inside.
			  The icon specifies the type of signal that is thrown when the end is
			  reached.
      </para>
           
      <para>
        The 'none end event' is drawn as a circle with thick border with no icon inside,
        which means that no signal is thrown when the execution reaches the event.
        The end activity in JPDL has the same semantics as the none end event.
      </para>
           
      <para>
        A none end event is defined as follows. An id is required, a name is optional.
        <programlisting>
&lt;endEvent id=&quot;end&quot; name=&quot;myEnd&quot; /&gt;            
        </programlisting>
       </para>
           
       <para>
          The following example shows a process with only a none start and end event:
          <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.none.start.end.event.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
       </para>
           
       <para>
          The corresponding executable XML for this process looks like this (omitting the 
          <emphasis>definitions</emphasis> root element for clarity)
          <programlisting>
  &lt;process id=&quot;noneStartEndEvent&quot; name=&quot;BPMN2 Example none start and end event&quot;&gt;

    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;startEvent id=&quot;start&quot; /&gt;</emphasis>

    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow1&quot; name=&quot;fromStartToEnd&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;start&quot; targetRef=&quot;end&quot; /&gt;

    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;endEvent id=&quot;end&quot; name=&quot;End&quot; /&gt;</emphasis>

  &lt;/process&gt;            
          </programlisting>
       </para>
           
       <para>
          A process instances can now be created by calling the 
          <emphasis role="bold">startProcessInstanceXXX</emphasis> operations.
          <programlisting>
ProcessInstance processInstance = executionService.startProcessInstanceByKey(&quot;noneStartEndEvent&quot;);
          </programlisting>
        </para>
        
    </section>
        
    <section id="terminateEndEvent">
        
      <title>Event: Terminate end event</title>
        
        <para>
          The difference between a 'terminate' and a <link linkend="noneEndEvent">'none' end event</link> 
          lies in the fact how a path of execution is treated (or a 'token' in BPMN 2.0 terminology).
          The 'terminate' end event will end the complete process instance, whereas the 'none' 
          end event will only end the current path of execution. They both don't throw anything
          when the end event is reached.
        </para>
          
        <para>
          A terminate end event is defined as follows. An id is required, a name is optional.
          <programlisting>
&lt;endEvent id=&quot;terminateEnd&quot; name=&quot;myTerminateEnd&quot;&gt;
  <emphasis role="bold">&lt;terminateEventDefinition/&gt;</emphasis>
&lt;/endEvent&gt;            
          </programlisting>
        </para>
          
        <para>
          A terminate end event is depicted as an end event (circle with thick border), 
          with a full circle as icon inside. In the following example, completing the 'task1'
          will end the process instance, while completing the 'task2' will only end the path
          of execution which enters the end event, leaving the task1 open.
          <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.terminate.end.event.example.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
          See the examples shipped with the jBPM distribution for the unit test and XML counterpart
          of this business process.
        </para>
        
    </section>
    
    <section id="sequenceFlow">
    
      <title>Sequence Flow</title>
      
      <para>
        A sequence flow is the connection between events, activities and gateways shown as a
        solid line with an arrow in a BPMN diagram (JPDL equivalent is the transition).
        Each sequence flow has exactly one <emphasis role="bold">source</emphasis> and exactly one 
        <emphasis role="bold">target</emphasis> reference, that contains the <emphasis role="bold">id</emphasis> 
        of an activity, event or gateway.
        <programlisting>
&lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;myFlow&quot; name=&quot;My Flow&quot; 
        sourceRef=&quot;sourceId&quot; targetRef=&quot;targetId&quot; /&gt;
        </programlisting>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        An important difference with JPDL is the behaviour of multiple outgoing sequence flows.
        In JPDL, only one transition is selected as outgoing transition, unless the activity
        is a fork (or a custom activity with fork behaviour). However, in BPMN, the standard behaviour
        of multiple outgoing sequence flow is to split the incoming token ('execution' in jBPM
        terminology) into a collection of tokens, one for each outgoing sequence flow. In the following
        situation, after completing the first task, there will be three tasks activated instead of one.
       <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.sequence.flow.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
       To avoid that a certain sequence flow is taken, one has to add a condition to the sequence flow.
       At runtime, only when the condition evaluates to true, that sequence flow will
       be taken.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        To put a condition on a sequence flow, add a <emphasis role="bold">conditionExpression
        </emphasis> element to the sequence flow. Conditions are to be put between <emphasis role="bold">
        ${}</emphasis>.
        <programlisting>
&lt;sequenceFlow id=....&gt;
  <emphasis role="bold">&lt;conditionExpression xsi:type=&quot;tFormalExpression&quot;&gt;${amount &gt;= 500}&lt;/conditionExpression&gt;</emphasis>   
&lt;/sequenceFlow&gt;    
        </programlisting>
        Note that is currently is necessary to add the <emphasis role="bold">
        xsi:type=&quot;tFormalExpression&quot;</emphasis> to the <emphasis role="bold">
        conditionExpression</emphasis>. A conditional sequence flow is visualized as a mini diamond
        shape at the beginning of the sequence flow. Keep in mind that conditions always can be defined 
        on sequence flow, but some constructs will not interprete them (eg. parallel gateway).
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Activities (such as the user task) and gateways (such as  the exclusive gateway) can have a
        default sequence flow. This default sequence flow is taken only when all the other outgoing
        sequence flow from an activity or gateway have a condition that evaluate to false. A
        default sequence flow is graphically visualized as a sequence flow with a 'slash marker'.
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.default.sequence.flow.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
        The default sequence flow is specified by filling in the <emphasis role="bold">'default'
        attribute </emphasis> of the activity or gateway.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         Also note that an expression on a default sequence flow is ignored.
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="gateway">
    
      <title>Gateways</title>
    
      <para>
        A gateway in BPMN is used to control the flow through the process. More specifically, 
        when a token (the BPMN 2.0 conceptual notion of an execution) arrives in a gateway, it can be merged 
        or split depending on the gateway type.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Gateways are depicted as a diamond shape, with an icon inside specifying the type 
        (exclusive, inclusive, etc.).
      </para>
      
      <para>
        On every gateway type, the attribute <emphasis role="bold">gatewayDirection</emphasis>
        can be set. following values are possible:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <emphasis role="bold">unspecificed (default)</emphasis>: the gateway may have multiple
            incoming and multiple sequence flow.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <emphasis role="bold">mixed</emphasis>: the gateway must have multiple incoming and
            multiple outgoing sequence flow.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <emphasis role="bold">converging</emphasis>: the gateway must have multiple incoming
            sequence flow, but can have only one outgoing sequence flow.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <emphasis role="bold">diverging</emphasis>: the gateway must have only one incoming
            sequence flow and multiple outgoing sequence flow.
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        Take for example the following example: a parallel gateway that has as gatewayDirection
        'converging', will have a join behaviour.
        <programlisting>
&lt;parallelGateway id=&quot;myJoin&quot; name=&quot;My synchronizing join&quot; gatewayDirection=&quot;converging&quot; />        
        </programlisting>
        <emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: the 'gatewayDirection' attribute is optional according 
        to the specification. This means that we cannot rely on this attribute at runtime to
        know which type of behaviour a certain gateway has (for example for a parallel gateway if
        we have joining of forking behaviour). However, the 'gatewayDirection' attribute is used at parsing 
        time as a constraint check for the incoming/outgoing sequence flow. So using this 
        attribute will lower the chance on errors when referencing sequence flow, but is not
        required.
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="exclusiveGateway">
    
      <title>Gateway: Exclusive Gateway</title>
      
      <para>
        An exclusive gateway represents an <emphasis role="bold">exclusive decision</emphasis>
        in the process. Exactly one outgoing sequence flow will be taken, depending on the conditions
        defined on the sequence flow.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The corresponding JPDL construct with the same semantics is the 
        <emphasis role="bold">decision</emphasis> activity. The full technical name of the 
        exclusive gateway is the <emphasis role="bold">'exclusive data-based gateway'</emphasis>,
        but it is also often called the <emphasis role="bold">XOR Gateway</emphasis>.
        The XOR gateway is depicted as a diamond with a 'X' icon inside. An empty diamond
        without a gateway also signifies an exclusive gateway.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The following diagram shows the usage of an exclusive gateway: depending on the value of the
        amount variable, one of the three outgoing sequence flow out of the exclusive gateway
        is chosen.
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.exclusive.gateway.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
        The corresponding executable XML of this process looks as follows.
        Note that the conditions are defined on the sequence flow. The exclusive gateway will select
        the single sequence flow for which its condition evaluates to true. If multiple conditions
        evaluate to true, the first one encountered will be taken (a log message will indicate
        this situation).
        <programlisting>
  &lt;process id=&quot;exclusiveGateway&quot; name=&quot;BPMN2 Example exclusive gateway&quot;&gt;

    &lt;startEvent id=&quot;start&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow1&quot; name=&quot;fromStartToExclusiveGateway&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;start&quot; targetRef=&quot;decideBasedOnAmountGateway&quot; /&gt;
      
   <emphasis role="bold">&lt;exclusiveGateway id=&quot;decideBasedOnAmountGateway&quot; name=&quot;decideBasedOnAmount&quot; /&gt;</emphasis>
   
   &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow2&quot; name=&quot;fromGatewayToEndNotEnough&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;decideBasedOnAmountGateway&quot; targetRef=&quot;endNotEnough&quot;&gt;
      <emphasis role="bold">&lt;conditionExpression xsi:type=&quot;tFormalExpression&quot;&gt;
        ${amount &lt; 100}
      &lt;/conditionExpression&gt;</emphasis>
   &lt;/sequenceFlow&gt;
      
   &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow3&quot; name=&quot;fromGatewayToEnEnough&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;decideBasedOnAmountGateway&quot; targetRef=&quot;endEnough&quot;&gt;
      <emphasis role="bold">&lt;conditionExpression xsi:type=&quot;tFormalExpression&quot;&gt;
        ${amount &lt;= 500 &amp;&amp; amount &gt;= 100}
        &lt;/conditionExpression&gt;</emphasis>
   &lt;/sequenceFlow&gt;
      
   &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow4&quot; name=&quot;fromGatewayToMoreThanEnough&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;decideBasedOnAmountGateway&quot; targetRef=&quot;endMoreThanEnough&quot;&gt;
      <emphasis role="bold">&lt;conditionExpression xsi:type=&quot;tFormalExpression&quot;&gt;
        ${amount &gt; 500}
      &lt;/conditionExpression&gt;</emphasis>
   &lt;/sequenceFlow&gt;   

   &lt;endEvent id=&quot;endNotEnough&quot; name=&quot;not enough&quot; /&gt;
   
   &lt;endEvent id=&quot;endEnough&quot; name=&quot;enough&quot; /&gt;
   
   &lt;endEvent id=&quot;endMoreThanEnough&quot; name=&quot;more than enough&quot; /&gt;

  &lt;/process&gt;        
        </programlisting>
        This process needs a variable such that the expression can be evaluated at runtime.
        Variables can be provided when starting the process instance (similar to JPDL):
        <programlisting>
Map&lt;String, Object&gt; vars = new HashMap&lt;String, Object&gt;();
vars.put(&quot;amount&quot;, amount);
ProcessInstance processInstance = executionService.startProcessInstanceByKey(&quot;exclusiveGateway&quot;, vars);        
        </programlisting>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The exclusive gateway requires that all outgoing sequence flow have conditions defined
        on them. An exception to this rule is the default sequence flow.
        Use the <emphasis role="bold">default attribute</emphasis> to reference an existing
        <emphasis role="bold">id of a sequence flow</emphasis>. This sequence flow will be taken
        when the conditions on the other outgoing sequence flow all evaluate to false.
        <programlisting>
&lt;exclusiveGateway id=&quot;decision&quot; name=&quot;decideBasedOnAmountAndBankType&quot; <emphasis role="bold">default=&quot;myFlow&quot;</emphasis>/&gt;
   
&lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;myFlow&quot; name=&quot;fromGatewayToStandard&quot;
    sourceRef=&quot;decision&quot; targetRef=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;
&lt;/sequenceFlow&gt;        
        </programlisting>
        An exclusive gateway can have both convering and diverging functionality. The logic is 
        easy to grasp: for every execution that arrives at the gateway, one outgoing sequence
        flow is selected to continue the flow.  The following diagram is completely legal in
        BPMN 2.0 (omitting names and conditions for clarity). 
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.exclusive.gateway.splitting.and.merging.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="parallelGateway">
    
      <title>Gateway: Parallel Gateway</title>
      
      <para>
        A parallel gateway is used to split or synchronize the respectively incoming or outgoing
        sequence flow.
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            A parallel gateway with one incoming sequence flow and more than one outgoing sequence
            flow is called a <emphasis role="bold">'parallel split</emphasis> or an 
            <emphasis role="bold">'AND-split'</emphasis>. All outgoing sequence flow are going to
            be taken in parallel. <emphasis role="bold">Note: as defined by the specification,
            conditions on the outgoing sequence flow are ignored.</emphasis>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            A parallel gateway with multiple incoming sequence flow and one outgoing sequence flow
            is called a <emphasis role="bold">'parallel join'</emphasis> or an 
            <emphasis role="bold">AND-join</emphasis>. All incoming sequence flow need to arrive
            in this parallel joing before the outgoing sequence flow is taken.
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        A parallel gateway is defined as follows:
        <programlisting>
&lt;parallelGateway id=&quot;myParallelGateway&quot; name=&quot;My Parallel Gateway&quot; />        
        </programlisting>
        Note that the 'gatewayDirection' attribute can be used to catch modeling errors at parsing 
        time (see above).
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The following diagram shows how a parallel gateway can be used. After process start,
        both the 'prepare shipment' and 'bill customer' user tasks will be active.
        The parallel gateway is depicted as a diamond shape with a plus icon inside, both for the 
        splitting and joining behaviour.
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.parallel.gateway.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
        The XML counterpart of this diagram looks as follows:
        <programlisting>
  &lt;process id=&quot;parallelGateway&quot; name=&quot;BPMN2 example parallel gatewar&quot;&gt;
  
    &lt;startEvent id=&quot;Start&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow1&quot; name=&quot;fromStartToSplit&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;Start&quot;
      targetRef=&quot;parallelGatewaySplit&quot;  /&gt;

    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;parallelGateway id=&quot;parallelGatewaySplit&quot; name=&quot;Split&quot; 
      gatewayDirection=&quot;diverging&quot;/&gt;</emphasis>

    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow2a&quot; name=&quot;Leg 1&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;parallelGatewaySplit&quot;
      targetRef=&quot;prepareShipment&quot; /&gt;
      
    &lt;userTask id=&quot;prepareShipment&quot; name=&quot;Prepare shipment&quot; 
      implementation=&quot;other&quot; /&gt;
    
    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow2b&quot; name=&quot;fromPrepareShipmentToJoin&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;prepareShipment&quot;
      targetRef=&quot;parallelGatewayJoin&quot;  /&gt;
      
    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow3a&quot; name=&quot;Leg 2&quot; 
      sourceRef=&quot;parallelGatewaySplit&quot;
      targetRef=&quot;billCustomer&quot; /&gt;
      
    &lt;userTask id=&quot;billCustomer&quot; name=&quot;Bill customer&quot; 
      implementation=&quot;other&quot; /&gt;
    
    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow3b&quot; name=&quot;fromLeg2ToJoin&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;billCustomer&quot;
      targetRef=&quot;parallelGatewayJoin&quot;  /&gt;

    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;parallelGateway id=&quot;parallelGatewayJoin&quot; name=&quot;Join&quot; 
      gatewayDirection=&quot;converging&quot;/&gt;</emphasis>
      
    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow4&quot; 
      sourceRef=&quot;parallelGatewayJoin&quot;
      targetRef=&quot;End&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/sequenceFlow&gt;

    &lt;endEvent id=&quot;End&quot; name=&quot;End&quot; /&gt;
    
  &lt;/process&gt;
        </programlisting>
        A parallel gateway (as is the case for any gateway) can have both splitting and 
        merging behaviour. The following diagram is completely legal BPMN 2.0. After process start,
        both task A and B will be active. When both A en B are completed, tasks C,D and E will be 
        active.                                 
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.parallel.gateway.splitting.and.merging.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </para>
      
    </section>
    
     <section id="inclusiveGateway">
    
      <title>Gateway: Inclusive Gateway</title>
      
      <para>
        An inclusive gateway - also called an <emphasis role="bold">OR-gateway</emphasis> - is used
        to 'conditionally' split or merge sequence flow. It basically behaves as a parallel 
        gateway, but it also takes in account conditions on the outgoing sequence flow (split behaviour)
        and calculates if there are executions left that could reach the gateway (merge behaviour).
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The inclusive gateway is depicted as a typical gateway shape with a circle inside (referring to 'OR' semantics).
        Unlike the exclusive gateway, all condition expressions are evaluated (diverging or 'split' behaviour).
        For every expression that evaluates to true, a new child execution is created. 
        Sequence flow without a condition will always be taken (ie. a child execution will always be
        created in that case). 
     </para>
     
     <para>
        A converging inclusive gateway ('merge' behaviour) has a somewhat more difficult execution logic.
        When an execution (Token in BPMN 2.0 terminology) arrives at the merging inclusive gateway, 
        the following is checked (quoting the specification literally): 
        
        <programlisting>
For each empty incoming sequence flow, there is no 
Token in the graph anywhere upstream of this sequence flow, i.e., there is no directed path 
(formed by Sequence Flow)  from a Token to this sequence flow unless 
a) the path visits the inclusive gateway or 
b) the path visits a node that has a directed path to a non-empty
   incoming sequence flow of the inclusive gateway. &quot;
        </programlisting>
        
        In more simple words: when an execution arrives at the gateway, all active execution are
        checked if they can reach the inclusive gateway, by only taking in account the sequence flow
        (note: conditions are not evaluated!). When the inclusive gateway is used, it is usally
        used in a pair of splitting/merging inclusive gateways. In those cases, the execution
        behaviour is easy enough to grasph by just looking at the model. 
        
     </para>
     
     <para>   
        Of course, it is not hard to imagine situations where the executions are split and merged 
        in complex combinations using a variety of constructs including the inclusive gateway.
        In those cases, it could very well be that the actual execution behaviour might not be what
        the modelers' expects. So be careful when using the inclusive gateway and keep in mind
        that it is often the best practice to use inclusive gateways just in pairs.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The following diagram shows how the inclusive gateway can be used.
        (example taken from &quot;BPMN method and style&quot; by Bruce Silver)
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.inclusive.gateway.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
        We can distinguish following cases:
        <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <emphasis role="bold">Cash more than 10000 and not a foreign bank: </emphasis>Only the
             &quot;Large deposit&quot; task will be active.
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <emphasis role="bold">Cash more than 10000 and a foreign bank: </emphasis> Both the 
             &quot;Large deposit&quot; and &quot;Foreign deposit&quot; task will be active.
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <emphasis role="bold">Cash lower than 10000 and a foreign bank: </emphasis> Only the 
             &quot;Foreign deposit&quot; task will be active.
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <emphasis role="bold">Cash lower than 10000 and not a foreign bank: </emphasis> In this 
             case, both expressions evaluate to false. The default sequence flow will now be chosen.
             In this example, this means that the &quot;Standard deposit&quot; task is active.
           </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        No matter how many tasks are active after going through the inclusive gateway, the converging
        inclusive gateway on the right will wait until all outgoing sequence flow of the inclusive
        gateway on the left have reached the merging gateway (sometimes only one, sometimes two). Take a look at 
        <emphasis role="bold">org.jbpm.examples.bpmn.gateway.inclusive.InclusiveGatewayTest</emphasis> 
        to see how this example reflects in a unit test.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The XML version of the example above looks as follows:
        <programlisting>
&lt;process id=&quot;inclusiveGateway&quot; name=&quot;BPMN2 Example inclusive gateway&quot;&gt;

    &lt;startEvent id=&quot;start&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow1&quot; sourceRef=&quot;start&quot; targetRef=&quot;inclusiveGatewaySplit&quot; /&gt;
   
   <emphasis role="bold">&lt;inclusiveGateway id=&quot;inclusiveGatewaySplit&quot; default=&quot;flow3&quot;/&gt;</emphasis>
   
   &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow2&quot; sourceRef=<emphasis role="bold">&quot;inclusiveGatewaySplit&quot;</emphasis> targetRef=&quot;largeDeposit&quot;&gt;
      &lt;conditionExpression xsi:type=&quot;tFormalExpression&quot;&gt;${cash &gt; 10000}&lt;/conditionExpression&gt;
   &lt;/sequenceFlow&gt;
      
   &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow3&quot; sourceRef=<emphasis role="bold">&quot;inclusiveGatewaySplit&quot;</emphasis> targetRef=&quot;standardDeposit&quot; /&gt;
      
   &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow4&quot; sourceRef=<emphasis role="bold">&quot;inclusiveGatewaySplit&quot;</emphasis> targetRef=&quot;foreignDeposit&quot;&gt;
      &lt;conditionExpression xsi:type=&quot;tFormalExpression&quot;&gt;${bank == 'foreign'}&lt;/conditionExpression&gt;
   &lt;/sequenceFlow&gt;   
   
   &lt;userTask id=&quot;largeDeposit&quot; name=&quot;Large deposit&quot; /&gt;
   
   &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow5&quot; sourceRef=&quot;largeDeposit&quot; targetRef=<emphasis role="bold">&quot;inclusiveGatewayMerge&quot;</emphasis> /&gt;
   
   &lt;userTask id=&quot;standardDeposit&quot; name=&quot;Standard deposit&quot; /&gt;
   
   &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow6&quot; sourceRef=&quot;standardDeposit&quot; targetRef=<emphasis role="bold">&quot;inclusiveGatewayMerge&quot;</emphasis> /&gt;
   
   &lt;userTask id=&quot;foreignDeposit&quot; name=&quot;Foreign deposit&quot; /&gt;
   
   &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow7&quot; sourceRef=&quot;foreignDeposit&quot; targetRef=<emphasis role="bold">&quot;inclusiveGatewayMerge&quot;</emphasis> /&gt;
   
   <emphasis role="bold">&lt;inclusiveGateway id=&quot;inclusiveGatewayMerge&quot; /&gt;</emphasis>
   
    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow8&quot; sourceRef=&quot;inclusiveGatewayMerge&quot; targetRef=&quot;theEnd&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;endEvent id=&quot;theEnd&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/process&gt;
        </programlisting>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        As with any gateway type, the inclusive gateway type can have both merging and splitting
        behaviour. In that case, the inclusive gateway will first wait until all executions
        have arrived, before splitting again for every sequence flow that has a condition
        that evauluates to true (or doesn't have a condition).
         <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.inclusive.gateway.merging.and.splitting.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </para>
      
    </section>  
    
    <section id="task">

      <title>Tasks</title>
    
      <para>
        A task represents work that needs to be done by an external
        entity, such as a human actor or an automated service.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        It's important to note that the BPMN semantics of a 'task' differ from the JPDL semantics.
        In JPDL, the concept 'task' is always used in the context of a human actor doing some 
        type of work. When the process engine encounters a task in JPDL, it will create a task in some human
        actor's task list and it will behave as a wait state. In BPMN 2.0 however, there are several
        task types, some indicating a wait state (eg. the <emphasis role="bold">User Task</emphasis>
        and some indicating an automatic activity (eg. the <emphasis role="bold">Service Task</emphasis>).
        So take good care not to confuse the meaning of the task concept when switching languages.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Tasks are depicted by a rounded rectangle, typically containing a text inside. The type
        of the task (user task, service task, script task, etc.) is shown as a little icon on the left top 
        corner of the rectangle. Depending on the task type, the engine will execute different 
        functionality.
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="userTask">
    
      <title>Task: User Task</title>
    
      <para>
        A <emphasis role="bold">User task</emphasis> is the typical 'human task' that is found
        in practically every workflow or BPM software out there. When process execution reaches
        such a user task, a new human task is created in task list for a given user.
     </para>
     
      <para>   
        The main difference with a <link linkend="manualTask">manual task</link> (which also signifies
        work for a human actor) is that the task is known to the process engine. The engine can 
        track the completion, assignee, time, etc which is not the case for a manual task.  
      </para>
      
      <para>
        A user task is depicted as a rounded rectangle with a small user icon in the top left corner.
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.user.task.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
        A user task is defined as follows in the BPMN 2.0 XML:
        <programlisting>
&lt;userTask id=&quot;myTask&quot; name=&quot;My task&quot; />      
        </programlisting> 
        According to the specification, multiple implementations are possible (Webservice, WS-humantask, etc.),
        as stated by using the <emphasis role="bold">implementation</emphasis> attribute.
        Currently, only the standard jBPM task mechanism is available, so there is no point (yet)
        in defining the 'implementation' attribute.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The BPMN 2.0 specification contains quite a few ways of assigning user tasks to user(s), 
        group(s), role(s), etc. The current BPMN 2.0 jBPM implementation allows to assign tasks using
        a <emphasis role="bold">resourceAssignmentExpression</emphasis>, combined
        with the <emphasis role="bold">humanPerformer or PotentialOwner</emphasis> construct.
        It is to be expected that this area will evolve future releases.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        A <emphasis role="bold">potentialOwner</emphasis> is used when you want to make a certain
        user, group, role, etc. a <emphasis role="bold">candidate</emphasis> for a certain task.
        Take the following example. Here the candidate group for the task 'My task' will be
        the 'management' group. Also note that a resource must be defined <emphasis role="bold">
        outside the process</emphasis>, such that the task assignment can reference the resource.
        In fact, any activity can reference one or more resource elements.
        Currently, only defining this resource is enough (since it is a required attribute by the spec),
        but this will be enhanced in a later release (eg. resources can have runtime parameters).
        <programlisting>
&lt;resource id=&quot;manager&quot; name=&quot;manager&quot; /> 

&lt;process ...&gt;

...        
        
&lt;userTask id=&quot;myTask&quot; name=&quot;My task&quot;&gt;
  &lt;potentialOwner resourceRef=&quot;manager&quot; jbpm:type=&quot;group&quot;&gt;
    &lt;resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
      &lt;formalExpression&gt;management&lt;/formalExpression&gt;
    &lt;/resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
  &lt;/potentialOwner&gt;
&lt;/userTask&gt;        
        </programlisting>
        Note that we are using a specific extension here 
        (<emphasis role="bold">jbpm:type=&quot;group&quot;</emphasis>), to define this is a group assignment.
        If this attribute is removed, the group semantics will be used as default (which would be 
        ok in this example).
        Now suppose that Peter and Mary are a member of the management group (here using the default
        identity service):
        <programlisting>
identityService.createGroup("management");
    
identityService.createUser("peter", "Peter", "Pan");
<emphasis role="bold">identityService.createMembership("peter", "management");</emphasis>
    
identityService.createUser("mary", "Mary", "Littlelamb");
<emphasis role="bold">identityService.createMembership("mary", "management");  </emphasis>      
        </programlisting>
        Then both peter and mary can look in their task list for this task (code snippet from the 
        example unit test):
        <programlisting>
// Peter and Mary are both part of management, so they both should see the task
List&lt;Task&gt; tasks = taskService.findGroupTasks(&quot;peter&quot;);
assertEquals(1, tasks.size());
<emphasis role="bold"> tasks = taskService.findGroupTasks(&quot;mary&quot;);</emphasis>
assertEquals(1, tasks.size());
    
// Mary claims the task
Task task = tasks.get(0);
taskService.takeTask(task.getId(), &quot;mary&quot;);
assertNull(taskService.createTaskQuery().candidate(&quot;peter&quot;).uniqueResult());
    
taskService.completeTask(task.getId());
assertProcessInstanceEnded(processInstance);        
        </programlisting>
        When the assignment should be done to a <emphasis role="bold">candidate user</emphasis>,
        just use the <emphasis role="bold">jbpm:type="user"</emphasis> attribute.
        <programlisting>
&lt;userTask id=&quot;myTask&quot; name=&quot;My User task&quot;&gt;
  &lt;potentialOwner resourceRef=&quot;employee&quot; <emphasis role="bold">jbpm:type=&quot;user&quot;</emphasis>&gt;
    &lt;resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
      &lt;formalExpression&gt;peter&lt;/formalExpression&gt;
    &lt;/resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
  &lt;/potentialOwner&gt;
&lt;/userTask&gt;        
        </programlisting>
        In this example, peter will be able to find the task since he's a candidate user for the task.
        <programlisting>
List&lt;Task&gt; tasks = taskService.createTaskQuery().candidate(&quot;peter&quot;).list();        
        </programlisting>
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <para>
      A <emphasis role="bold">human performer</emphasis> is used when you want to assign a task
      directly to a certain user, group, role, etc. The way to do this looks very much
      like that of the potential owner.
      <programlisting>
&lt;resource id="employee" name="employee" /&gt;      

&lt;process ...&gt;

...        
         
&lt;userTask id="myTask" name="My User task"&gt;
  <emphasis role="bold">&lt;humanPerformer resourceRef="employee"&gt;</emphasis>
    &lt;resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
      &lt;formalExpression&gt;mary&lt;/formalExpression&gt;
    &lt;/resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
  &lt;/humanPerformer&gt;
&lt;/userTask&gt;      
      </programlisting>
      In this example, the task will be directly assigned to Mary. She can now find the task
      in her task list:
      <programlisting>
List&lt;Task&gt; tasks = taskService.findPersonalTasks(&quot;mary&quot;);       
      </programlisting>
      
      
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Since the task assignment is done through the use of a 
      <emphasis role="bold">formalExpression</emphasis>, it's also possible to define expressions
      that are evaluated at runtime. The expressions itself need to be put inside a 
      <emphasis role="bold">${}</emphasis>, as usual in jBPM.
      For example, if a process variable 'user' is defined, then  it can be used inside an expression.
      More complex expressions are of course possible.
      <programlisting>
&lt;userTask id="myTask" name="My User task"&gt;
  &lt;humanPerformer resourceRef="employee"&gt;
    &lt;resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
      <emphasis role="bold">&lt;formalExpression&gt;${user}&lt;/formalExpression&gt;</emphasis>
    &lt;/resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
  &lt;/humanPerformer&gt;
&lt;/userTask&gt;         
      </programlisting>
      Note that it is not needed to use the 'jbpm:type' on a humanPerformer element, since only
      direct user assignments can be done. If a task needs to be assigned to a role or group, 
      use the potentialOwner with a group type (when you assign a task to a group, all members
      of that group will always be candidate users for that group - hence the usage of 
      potentialOwner).
    </para>
    
    <section id="serviceTask">
    
      <title>Task: Java Service Task</title>
      
      <para>
        A <emphasis role="bold">Service Task</emphasis> is an automatic activity that calls some 
        sort of service, such as a web service, Java service, etc. Currently, only Java service
        invocations are supported by the jBPM engine, but Web service invocations are planned 
        for a future release.
          <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.service.task.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Defining a service task requires quite a few lines of XML (the BPEL influence is certainly
        visible here). Of course, in the near future, we expect that tooling will simplify this area
        a lot. A service task is defined as follows:
        <programlisting>
&lt;serviceTask id=&quot;MyServiceTask&quot; name=&quot;My service task&quot; 
  implementation=&quot;Other&quot; operationRef=&quot;myOperation&quot; /&gt;
        </programlisting>
        The service task has a required <emphasis role="bold">id</emphasis> and an optional
        <emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis>. The <emphasis role="bold">implementation</emphasis>
        attribute is used to indicate what the type of the invoked service is. Possible values
        are WebService, Other or Unspecified. Since we've only implemented the Java invocation,
        only the <emphasis role="bold">Other</emphasis> choice will do something useful for the moment.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The service task will invoke a certain operation that is referenced by the 
        <emphasis role="bold">operationRef</emphasis> attribute using the id of an 
        <emphasis role="bold">operation</emphasis>. Such an operation is part of an 
        <emphasis role="bold">interface</emphasis> as shown below. Every operation has 
        at least one <emphasis role="bold">input message</emphasis> and at most one
        <emphasis role="bold">output message</emphasis>.
        <programlisting>
&lt;interface id=&quot;myInterface&quot;
    name=&quot;org.jbpm.MyJavaServicek&quot;&gt;
    &lt;operation id=&quot;myOperation2&quot; name=&quot;myMethod&quot;&gt;
      &lt;inMessageRef&gt;inputMessage&lt;/inMessageRef&gt;
      &lt;outMessageRef&gt;outputMessage&lt;/outMessageRef&gt;
    &lt;/bpmn:operation&gt;
&lt;/interface&gt;        
        </programlisting>
        For a Java service, the <emphasis role="bold">name of the interface</emphasis> is used
        to specificy the fully qualified classname of the Java class. The <emphasis role="bold">
        name of the operation</emphasis> is then used to specify the name of the method
        that must be called. The input/output message that represent the parameters/return value of
        the Java method are defined as follows:
        <programlisting>
&lt;message id=&quot;inputMessage&quot; name=&quot;input message&quot; structureRef=&quot;myItemDefinition1&quot; /&gt;        
        </programlisting>
        Several elements in BPMN are so-called 'item-aware', including this message construct.
        This means that they are involved in storing or reading items during process execution.
        The data structure to hold these elements is specified using a reference to an 
        <emphasis role="bold">ItemDefinition</emphasis>. In this context, the message specifies 
        its data structure by referencing an Itemdefinition in the 
        <emphasis role="bold">structureRef</emphasis> attribute.
        <programlisting>
        
  &lt;itemDefinition id=&quot;myItemDefinition1&quot; &gt;
    &lt;jbpm:arg&gt;
      &lt;jbpm:object expr=&quot;#{var1}&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/jbpm:arg&gt;
  &lt;/itemDefinition&gt;
  
  &lt;itemDefinition id=&quot;myItemDefinition2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;jbpm:var name=&quot;returnVar&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/itemDefinition&gt;
          
        </programlisting>
        Do note that this is not fully standard BPMN 2.0 as by the specification (hence the 'jbpm' prefix).
        In fact, according to the specification, the ItemDefinition shouldn't contain more
        than a data structure definition. The actual mapping between input paramaters, with a ceratin
        data structure, is done in the <emphasis role="bold">ioSpecification</emphasis> section
        of the serviceTask. However, the current jBPM BPMN 2.0 implementation hasn't implemented
        that construct yet. So, this means that the current usage as described above, will probably 
        change in the near future.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Important note: Interfaces, ItemDefinitions and messages are
        defined outside a &lt;process&gt;.</emphasis> See the example <emphasis role="bold">
        ServiceTaskTest</emphasis> for a concrete process and unit test.
      </para> 
    
    </section>  
    
    <section id="scriptTask">
    
      <title>Task: Script Task</title>
    
      <para>
        A script task is a an automatic activity upon which the process engine will execute 
        a script when the task is reached. The script task is used as follows:
        <programlisting>
&lt;scriptTask id=&quot;scriptTask&quot; name=&quot;Script Task&quot; scriptLanguage=&quot;bsh&quot;&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;&lt;![CDATA[
    for(int i=0; i &lt; input.length; i++){
      System.out.println(input[i] + &quot; x 2 = &quot; + (input[i]*2));
    }]]&gt;
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/scriptTask&gt;       
        </programlisting>
        The script task, besides the required <emphasis role="bold">id</emphasis> and the optional
        <emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis>, allows for specifying a <emphasis role="bold">
        scriptLanguage</emphasis> and a <emphasis role="bold">script</emphasis>. 
        Since we're using JSR-223 ('Scripting for the Java platform'), changing the script language involves
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>changing the <emphasis role="bold">scriptLanguage</emphasis> attribute to the JSR-223 compliant name</listitem>
          <listitem>adding the ScriptEngine implementation of the JSR specification to the classpath</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        The XML above is visualized as follows (adding a none start and end event).
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.script.task.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      
      <para>
        As shown in the example, process variables can be used inside the scripts. We can now start
        a process instance for this example process, while also supplying some random input variables:
        <programlisting>
Map&lt;String, Object&gt; variables = new HashMap&lt;String, Object&gt;();
Integer[] values = { 11, 23, 56, 980, 67543, 8762524 };
variables.put(&quot;input&quot;, values);   
executionService.startProcessInstanceBykey(&quot;scriptTaskExample&quot;, variables);     
        </programlisting>
        In the output console, we can now see the script being executed:
        <programlisting>
11 x 2 = 22
23 x 2 = 46
56 x 2 = 112
980 x 2 = 1960
67543 x 2 = 135086
8762524 x 2 = 17525048        
        </programlisting>
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="manualTask">
    
      <title>Task: Manual task</title>
      
      <para>
         <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.manual.task.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
         A manual task is a task that is performed by an external actor, but without the aid of 
         a BPM system or a service that is invoked. In the real world, examples are plenty:
         the installation of telephone system, sending of a letter using regular mail, calling 
         a customer by phone, etc.
         <programlisting>
&lt;manualTask id=&quot;myManualTask&quot; name=&quot;Call customer&quot; /&gt;         
         </programlisting>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The purpose of the manual task is more documentation/modeling-wise, as it has no meaning for
        execution on a process engine. As such, the process engine will simply pass through
        a manual task when it encounters one.
      </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="receiveTaskJava">
    
      <title>Task: Java Receive task</title>
      
      <para>
        A <emphasis role="bold">receive task</emphasis> is a task that waits for the arrival of 
        an external message. Besides the obvious use case involving webservices, the specification
        is liberal in what to do in other environments. The web service use case is not yet 
        implemented, but the receive task can already be used in a Java environment.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The receive task is depicted as a rounded rectangle (= task shape) with a little enveloppe
        in the left top corner.
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.receive.task.java.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        In a Java environment, the receive task without any other attribute filled in besides
        an id and (optionally) a name, behaves as a wait state. To introduce a wait state in your
        business process, just add the following line:
        <programlisting>
&lt;receiveTask id=&quot;receiveTask&quot; name=&quot;wait&quot; /&gt;        
        </programlisting>
        Process execution will wait in such a receive task. The process can then be continued
        using the familiar jBPM <emphasis role="bold">signal methods</emphasis>. Note that
        this will probably change in the future, since a 'signal' has a completely different
        meaning in BPMN 2.0.
        <programlisting>
Execution execution = processInstance.findActiveExecutionIn(&quot;receiveTask&quot;);
executionService.signalExecutionById(execution.getId());        
        </programlisting>
      </para>
    
    </section>
  
  </section> <!-- End of basic constructs section -->
  
  <section id="advancedConstructs">
  
    <title>Advanced constructs</title>
    
    <section id="embeddedSubProcess">
    
      <title>Embedded sub-process</title>
      
      <para>
        Subprocesses are in the first place a way of making a process "hierarchical", meaning that 
        a modeller can create several 'levels' of detail. The top level view then explains the 
        high-level way of doing things, while the lowest level focusses on the nitty gritty 
        details.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Take for example the following diagram. In this model, only the high level steps are shown.
        The actual implementation of the &quot;Check credit&quot; step is hidden behind a
        <emphasis role="bold">collapsed subprocess</emphasis>, which may be the perfect level
        of detail to discuss business processes with end-users.
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.collapsed.subprocess.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The second major use case for sub-processes is that the sub-process &quot;container&quot;
        acts as a scope for events. When an event is fired from within the sub-process, the catch 
        events on the boundary of the sub-process will be the first to receive this event.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        A sub-process that is defined within a top-level process is called an <emphasis role="bold">
        embeddable sub-process</emphasis>. All process data that is available in the parent
        process is also available in the sub-process. The following diagram shows the expanded
        version of the model above.
         <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.embedded.subprocess.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
         The XML counterpart of this model looks as follows:$
         <programlisting>
&lt;process id=&quot;embeddedSubprocess&quot;&gt;

    &lt;startEvent id=&quot;theStart&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow1&quot; sourceRef=&quot;theStart&quot; targetRef=&quot;receiveOrder&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;receiveTask name=&quot;Receive order&quot; id=&quot;receiveOrder&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow2&quot; sourceRef=&quot;receiveOrder&quot; targetRef=&quot;checkCreditSubProcess&quot; /&gt;
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;subProcess id=&quot;checkCreditSubProcess&quot; name=&quot;Credit check&quot;&gt;</emphasis>
    
      ...

    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;/subProcess&gt;</emphasis>
    
    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow9&quot; sourceRef=&quot;checkCreditSubProcess&quot; targetRef=&quot;theEnd&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;endEvent id=&quot;theEnd&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/process&gt;
         </programlisting>
         Note that inside the sub-process, events, activities, tasks are defined as if it were
         a top-level process (hence the three &quot;...&quot; within the XML example above. Sub-processes
         are <emphasis role="bold">only allowed to have a none start event</emphasis>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Conceptually an embedded sub-process works as follows: when an execution arrives
        at the subprocess, a child execution is created. The child execution can then later create
        other (sub-)child executions, for example when a parallel gateway is used whithin the
        sub-process. The sub-process however, is only completed when no executions are active anymore
        within the subprocess. In that case, the parent execution is taken for further continuation
        of the process.
      </para>
      <para>   
        For example, in the following diagram, the &quot;Third task&quot;
        will only be reached after both the &quot;First task&quot; and the &quot;Second task&quot;
        are completed. Completing one of the tasks in the sub-process, will not trigger the
        continuation of the sub-process, since one execution is still active within the sub-process.
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.subprocess.two.endevents.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Sub-processes can have multiple start events. In that case, multiple parallel paths
        will exist within the sub-process. The rules for sub-process completion are unchanged:
        the sub-process will only be left when all the executions of the parallel paths are
        ended.
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.subprocess.parallel.paths.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Nested sub-processes are also possible. This way, the process can be divided into several
        levels of detail. There is no limitation on the levels of nesting.
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.subprocess.nested.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Implementation note: According to the BPMN 2 specification, an activity without ougoing sequence
        flow implicitly ends the current execution. However currently, it is necessary for a correct functioning to  
        specifically use an end event within the sub-process to end a certain path. This will
        be enhanced in the future to be specification-compliant.
      </para>
    
    </section> <!-- End of embedded subprocess -->
    
    <section id="Timer start event">
    
      <title>Timer start event</title>
      
      <para>
        A timer start event is used to indicate that a process should be started when a given
        time condition is met. This could be a specific point in time (eg. October 10th, 2010 at
        5am), but also and more typically a recurring time (eg. every Friday at midnight).  
      </para>  
      
      <para>
        A timer start event is visualized as a circle with the clock icon inside.
       <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.timer.start.event.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Using a Timer Start event is done by adding a <emphasis role="bold">timerEventDefinition</emphasis>
        element below the startEvent element:
        <programlisting>
&lt;startEvent name=&quot;Every Monday morning&quot; id=&quot;myStart&quot;&gt;
  <emphasis role="bold">&lt;timerEventDefinition/&gt;</emphasis>
&lt;/startEvent&gt;        
        </programlisting>
        Following time definitions are possible:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <emphasis role="bold">timeDate: </emphasis>specifies a fixed date when a process instance
            must be created. The default format of the date specification is
            &quot;dd/MM/yyyy hh:mm:ss&quot;. This can engine-wide be changed by setting the 
            <emphasis role="bold">jbpm.duedatetime.format</emphasis> property in the configuration.
            <programlisting>
&lt;startEvent id=&quot;myStartEvent&quot; &gt;
  &lt;timerEventDefinition&gt;
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;timeDate&gt;10/10/2099 00:00:00&lt;/timeDate&gt;</emphasis>
  &lt;/timerEventDefinition&gt;
&lt;/startEvent&gt;           
            </programlisting>
            Note that using a fixed duedate makes the process only useable for a single time.
            After the process instance is created, the timer start event will never fire again.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <emphasis role="bold">timeCycle: </emphasis>specifies the recurring time when a new
            process instance will be created. Two types are possible

            <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Duration expression: </emphasis> 
                <programlisting>
quantity [business] {second | seconds | minute | minutes | 
                     hour | hours | day | days | week | 
                     weeks | month | months | year | years}                
                </programlisting>
                 This is completely similar to a timer duration definition in JPDL. Note that the 
                 BPMN2 start timer event also understands &quot;business time&quot;. This
                 allows for example to define a &quot;business day&quot; as an interval from
                 9am to 5pm. This way, the time from 5pm to 9am will not be taken in account when
                 the time on which the event will fire is calculated. 
                 Please refer to the JPDL userguide for more details on how this business calendar can be customized.
                 The following example shows a timer start event that will start a new process
                 instance every five hours.
                 <programlisting>
&lt;startEvent id=&quot;myStartEvent&quot; &gt;
  &lt;timerEventDefinition&gt;
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;timeCycle&gt;5 hours&lt;/timeCycle&gt;</emphasis>
  &lt;/timerEventDefinition&gt;
&lt;/startEvent&gt;               
                 </programlisting>
              </para>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CRON_expression">Cron expression:</ulink></emphasis>
                altough duration expressions cover already a great deal of recurring time definitions, 
                sometimes they are not easy to use. 
                When for example a process instance should be started every Friday night 23pm,
                cron expressions allow a more natural way of defining such repeating occurrences.
              </para>
              <para>
                The following example shows a timer start event that will start a new process
                instance every Friday at 23pm. 
                <programlisting>
&lt;startEvent id=&quot;myStartEvent&quot; &gt;
  &lt;timerEventDefinition&gt;
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;timeCycle&gt;0 0 23 ? * FRI&lt;/timeCycle&gt;</emphasis>
&lt;/timerEventDefinition&gt;
&lt;/startEvent&gt;               
                </programlisting>
              </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The timer start event implementation in jBPM also has following features:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            Process definitions that have a timer start event, can be started as if it also
            were a none start event. This means that calling for example 
            executionService.startProcessInstanceByKey(key) just works.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            The timer start event is internally implemented as a scheduled job. This means
            that a <emphasis role="bold">job executor</emphasis> has to be configured for
            the timer start event to work. The advantage of this implementation is that the
            timer start event firing is transactional (eg. if a service tasks right after the 
            timer start event fails, the transaction will be rolled back and the timer start event
            will be retried later) and able to cope with a server crash (ie. the when the server
            comes back up, the timer start event will be picked up by the job executor just as if
            nothing has happened).
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            When a new version of a process definition with a timer start event is deployed, the
            old timer start event job is removed from the system. This means that 
            <emphasis role="bold">only the latest version of the process definition will be used</emphasis>
            to create a new process instances.
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>        
      </para>
    
    </section> <!-- end of Timer start event -->
    
    <section id="intermediateEvents">
    
      <title>Intermediate events</title>
      
      <para>
        An intermediate event is used to model something that happens during a process (ie. after
        the process has started and before it is ended). Intermediate events are visualized as
        a circle with a double border, with an icon indicating the event type within the circle.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        There are several intermediate event types, such as a timer event, signal event, escalation
        event, etc. Intermediate events can be either throwing or catching:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <emphasis role="bold">Throwing: </emphasis>when an execution arrives in the event, it 
            immediately fires a certain trigger (a signal, an error, etc.). Throwing events can
            be graphically recognized by the icon that is filled in with black.
          </listitem>
           <listitem>
            <emphasis role="bold">Catching: </emphasis>when an execution arrives in the event,
            it will wait for a certain trigger to happen (an error, a timer, etc.). Catching events
            can be graphically recognized by the icon that is not filled with black (ie. white inside).
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    
    </section> <!-- end of intermediate events -->
    
    <section id="intermediateCatchTimer">
    
      <title>Intermediate catch event: Timer </title>
      
      <para>
        An intermediate timer event is used to represent a <emphasis role="bold">delay</emphasis>
        in the process. Straightfoward use cases are for example polling of data, executing
        heavy logic only at night when nobody is working, etc.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Note that an intermediate timer only can be used as a catch event (throwing a timer event
        makes no sense). The following diagram shows how the intermediate timer event is visualized.
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.intermediate.timer.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
        Defining an intermediate timer event is done in XML as follows:
        <programlisting>
&lt;intermediateCatchEvent id=&quot;myTimer&quot; name=&quot;Wait for an hour&quot;&gt;
  &lt;timerEventDefinition&gt;
    &lt;timeCycle&gt;1 hour&lt;/timeCycle&gt;
  &lt;/timerEventDefinition&gt;
&lt;/intermediateCatchEvent&gt;        
        </programlisting>
        There are two ways to specify the delay, using either a <emphasis role="bold">timeCycle
        or a timeDate</emphasis>. In the example above, a timeCycle is used.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Following delay definitions are possible (similar to those for a Timer Start Event).
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <emphasis role="bold">timeDate: </emphasis>specifies a fixed date when the timer will
            fire and the process continues. The default format of the date specification is
            &quot;dd/MM/yyyy hh:mm:ss&quot;. This can engine-wide be changed by setting the 
            <emphasis role="bold">jbpm.duedatetime.format</emphasis> property in the configuration.
            <programlisting>
&lt;intermediateCatchEvent id=&quot;myTimer&quot; &gt;
  &lt;timerEventDefinition&gt;
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;timeDate&gt;10/10/2099 00:00:00&lt;/timeDate&gt;</emphasis>
  &lt;/timerEventDefinition&gt;
&lt;/intermediateCatchEvent&gt;           
            </programlisting>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <emphasis role="bold">timeCycle: </emphasis>specifies a delay duration relative to the
            time when the execution enters the timer event. Two types are possible

            <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Duration expression: </emphasis> 
                <programlisting>
quantity [business] {second | seconds | minute | minutes | 
                     hour | hours | day | days | week | 
                     weeks | month | months | year | years}                
                </programlisting>
                 This is completely similar to a timer duration definition in JPDL. Note that the 
                 BPMN2 intermediate timer event also understands &quot;business time&quot;. This
                 allows for example to define a &quot;business day&quot; as an interval from
                 9am to 5pm. Timers that are started at 4pm with a duration of 2 hours, will fire
                 at 10am the next business day. Please refer to the JPDL userguide for more details
                 on how this business calendar can be customized.
                 <programlisting>
&lt;intermediateCatchEvent id=&quot;intermediateTimer&quot; &gt;
  &lt;timerEventDefinition&gt;
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;timeCycle&gt;5 hours&lt;/timeCycle&gt;</emphasis>
  &lt;/timerEventDefinition&gt;
&lt;/intermediateCatchEvent&gt;               
                 </programlisting>
              </para>
              <para>
	              <emphasis role="bold">Cron expression: </emphasis>altough duration expressions cover
	              already a great deal of delay definitions, sometimes they are not easy to use. When
	              for example the process should be delayed until Friday night 23pm such that the
	              processes can be executed in the weekend, duration expressions are hard to use
	              (you need something like &quot;#{calculated_value} seconds&quot;, where you need
	              to calculate the value first).
	            </para>
	            <para>
	             <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CRON_expression">Cron expressions</ulink>
	             allow to define delays in a way many people know (since cron expressions
	             are used to define scheduled task on Unix machines). Note that a cron expression
	             typically is used to define repetion. In this context however, the 
	             <emphasis role="bold">first point in time where the cron expression is satisfied</emphasis>
	             is used to set the due date of the timer event (so no repetition). The following example
	             shows how an intermediate timer event can be specified to continue the process
	             the next friday night at 23pm.
	             <programlisting>
&lt;intermediateCatchEvent id=&quot;intermediateTimer&quot; &gt;
  &lt;timerEventDefinition&gt;
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;timeCycle&gt;0 0 23 ? * FRI&lt;/timeCycle&gt;</emphasis>
      &lt;/timerEventDefinition&gt;
&lt;/intermediateCatchEvent&gt;               
	             </programlisting>
	            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    
    </section> <!-- end of intermediate catch event -->
    
  </section> <!-- End of advanced constructs -->
    
    
      
  <section id="completeExample">
  
    <title>Complete example (including console task forms)</title>
    
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Prerequisites</emphasis>: to run the example, we assume that a working
      jBPM console has been installed on your JBoss server. If not, please run the 'demo.setup.jboss' 
      install script first.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The business process we're implementing looks as follows:
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.vacationrequest.example.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
			You might recognize this example, since weve also implemented it in
			JPDL as an example in our distribution.
		</para>
		<para>
			The business process is simple: an employee can start a new process and
			make a request for a certain amount of vacation days. After the request
			task has been completed, the manager will find a verification task in
			its tasklist. The Manager can now decide to accept or reject this
			request. Depending on the outcome (thats the little rhombus on the
			outgoing sequence flow - it means there is a conditional expression on the sequence flow),
			a rejection message is send or the process ends. Do note that in fact we've used a shortcut
			here: instead of putting expressions on the outgoing sequence flow of the 'verify request'
			task, we've could have used an exclusive gateway after the user task to control the flow
			through the process. Also note that since we haven't implemented swimlanes yet (probably
			the next release), it's difficult to actually see who does what in the business process.
    </para> 
    
    <para>
      The XML version of this process looks as follows:
      <programlisting>
&lt;process id=&quot;vacationRequestProcess&quot; name=&quot;BPMN2 Example process using task forms&quot;&gt;

    &lt;startEvent id=&quot;start&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow1&quot; name=&quot;fromStartToRequestVacation&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;start&quot; targetRef=&quot;requestVacation&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;userTask id=&quot;requestVacation&quot; name=&quot;Request Vacation&quot;
      implementation=&quot;other&quot;&gt;
     &lt;potentialOwner resourceRef=&quot;user&quot; jbpm:type=&quot;group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
          &lt;formalExpression&gt;user&lt;/formalExpression&gt;
        &lt;/resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
      &lt;/potentialOwner&gt;
      &lt;rendering id=&quot;requestForm&quot;&gt;
        &lt;jbpm:form&gt;org/jbpm/examples/bpmn/usertask/taskform/request_vacation.ftl&lt;/jbpm:form&gt;
      &lt;/rendering&gt;
    &lt;/userTask&gt;

    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow2&quot;
      name=&quot;fromRequestVacationToVerifyRequest&quot; sourceRef=&quot;requestVacation&quot;
      targetRef=&quot;verifyRequest&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;userTask id=&quot;verifyRequest&quot; name=&quot;Verify Request&quot;
      implementation=&quot;other&quot;&gt;
      &lt;potentialOwner resourceRef=&quot;user&quot; jbpm:type=&quot;group&quot;&gt;
        &lt;resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
          &lt;formalExpression&gt;manager&lt;/formalExpression&gt;
        &lt;/resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
      &lt;/potentialOwner&gt;
      &lt;rendering id=&quot;verifyForm&quot;&gt;
        &lt;jbpm:form&gt;org/jbpm/examples/bpmn/usertask/taskform/verify_request.ftl&lt;/jbpm:form&gt;
      &lt;/rendering&gt;
    &lt;/userTask&gt;

    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow3&quot; name=&quot;fromVerifyRequestToEnd&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;verifyRequest&quot; targetRef=&quot;theEnd&quot;&gt;
      &lt;conditionExpression xsi:type=&quot;tFormalExpression&quot;&gt;
        ${verificationResult == 'OK'}
      &lt;/conditionExpression&gt;
    &lt;/sequenceFlow&gt;

    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow4&quot;
      name=&quot;fromVerifyRequestToSendRejectionMessage&quot; sourceRef=&quot;verifyRequest&quot;
      targetRef=&quot;sendRejectionMessage&quot;&gt;
      &lt;conditionExpression xsi:type=&quot;tFormalExpression&quot;&gt;
        ${verificationResult == 'Not OK'}
      &lt;/conditionExpression&gt;
    &lt;/sequenceFlow&gt;

    &lt;scriptTask id=&quot;sendRejectionMessage&quot; name=&quot;Send rejection Message&quot;
      scriptLanguage=&quot;bsh&quot;&gt;
      &lt;script&gt;
        &lt;![CDATA[System.out.println(&quot;Vacation request refused!&quot;);]]&gt;
      &lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;/scriptTask&gt;

    &lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow5&quot;
      name=&quot;fromSendRejectionMessageToEnd&quot; sourceRef=&quot;sendRejectionMessage&quot;
      targetRef=&quot;theEnd&quot; /&gt;

    &lt;endEvent id=&quot;theEnd&quot; name=&quot;End&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/process&gt;          
      </programlisting>
      <emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: this example is already installed when you've 
      used the demo setup. Also note that we're using a Script Task here, to quickly write
      something as output instead of sending a real message (the diagram is showing a Service
      Task). Also note that we've taken some shortcuts here regarding task assignment (will
      be fixed in the next release).
    </para>
 
    <para>
      The constructs used in this implementation are all covered in the previous section.
      Also note that we're using the <emphasis role="bold">taskform functionality</emphasis> 
      here, which is a custom jBPM extension for the <emphasis role="bold">rendering</emphasis>
      element of a User task.
      <programlisting>
&lt;userTask id=&quot;verifyRequest&quot; name=&quot;Verify Request&quot;
       implementation=&quot;other&quot;&gt;
  &lt;potentialOwner resourceRef=&quot;user&quot; jbpm:type=&quot;group&quot;&gt;
    &lt;resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
      &lt;formalExpression&gt;user&lt;/formalExpression&gt;
    &lt;/resourceAssignmentExpression&gt;
  &lt;/potentialOwner&gt;
  &lt;rendering id=&quot;verifyForm&quot;&gt;
    &lt;jbpm:form&gt;org/jbpm/examples/bpmn/usertask/taskform/verify_request.ftl&lt;/jbpm:form&gt;
  &lt;/rendering&gt;
&lt;/userTask&gt;
      </programlisting>  
      The mechanism regarding task forms for BPMN 2.0 is complete equivalent to that of JPDL.
      The form itself is a <ulink url="http://freemarker.org/">Freemarker</ulink> template file
      that needs to be incorporated in the deployment. For example, the 'verify_request.ftl' form
      looks like as follows.
      <programlisting>
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;

    &lt;form action=&quot;${form.action}&quot; method=&quot;POST&quot; enctype=&quot;multipart/form-data&quot;&gt;
    
      &lt;h3&gt;Your employee, <emphasis role="bold">${employee_name}</emphasis> would like to go on vacation&lt;/h3&gt;
      Number of days: <emphasis role="bold">${number_of_days}&lt;</emphasis>br/&gt;
      
      &lt;hr&gt;
      
      In case you reject, please provide a reason:&lt;br/&gt;
      <emphasis role="bold">&lt;input type=&quot;textarea&quot; name=&quot;reason&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</emphasis>
     
      <emphasis role="bold">&lt;input type=&quot;submit&quot; name=&quot;verificationResult&quot; value=&quot;OK&quot;&gt;
      &lt;input type=&quot;submit&quot; name=&quot;verificationResult&quot; value=&quot;Not OK&quot;&gt;</emphasis>
      
    &lt;/form&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;      
      </programlisting>
      Note that <emphasis role="bold">process variables can be 
      accessed using the ${my_process_variable} construct.</emphasis> Also note that named
      input controls (eg. input field, submit button) can be used to 
      <emphasis role="bold">define new process variables</emphasis>. 
      For example, the text input of the following field will be stored as the process
      variable 'reason'
      <programlisting>
&lt;input type=&quot;textarea&quot; name=&quot;reason&quot;/&gt;     
      </programlisting>
      Note that there are two submit buttons (which makes sense if you look at the 'OK' and 'Not OK'
      sequence flows going out the 'request vacation' task. By pressing one of these buttons, the
      process variable 'verificationResult' will be stored. It can then be used to evaluate the
      outgoing sequence flow:
      <programlisting>
&lt;sequenceFlow id=&quot;flow3&quot; name=&quot;fromVerifyRequestToEnd&quot;
      sourceRef=&quot;verifyRequest&quot; targetRef=&quot;theEnd&quot;&gt;
  &lt;conditionExpression xsi:type=&quot;tFormalExpression&quot;&gt;
    <emphasis role="bold">${verificationResult == 'OK'}</emphasis>
  &lt;/conditionExpression&gt;
&lt;/sequenceFlow&gt;      
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The process can now be deployed. You can use the ant deploy task for this (see examples),
      or you can point your jBPM configuration to the database of the console. To deploy
      your process programmatically, you need to add the task forms to your deployment:
      <programlisting>
NewDeployment deployment = repositoryService.createDeployment();
deployment.addResourceFromClasspath(&quot;org/jbpm/examples/bpmn/usertask/taskform/vacationrequest.bpmn.xml&quot;);
deployment.addResourceFromClasspath(&quot;org/jbpm/examples/bpmn/usertask/taskform/request_vacation.ftl&quot;);
deployment.addResourceFromClasspath(&quot;org/jbpm/examples/bpmn/usertask/taskform/verify_request.ftl&quot;);
deployment.deploy();      
      </programlisting>
      You can now embed (or run on a standalone server) this business process, by using the 
      familiar jBPM API operations. For example, process instances can now be started using the 
      key (ie. the process id for BPMN 2.0):
      <programlisting>
ProcessInstance pi = executionService.startProcessInstanceByKey(&quot;vacationRequestProcess&quot;);      
      </programlisting>
      Or tasks list can be retrieved:
      <programlisting>
Task requestTasktask = taskService.createTaskQuery().candidate(&quot;peter&quot;).uniqueResult();      
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      When deploying to the jBPM console database, you should see our new business process popping up.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.vacationrequest.example.console.01.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      
      After you start a new process, a new task should be available in the employee's tasklist.
      When clicking on 'view', the task form will be displayed, requesting to fill in some
      variables for further use in the process.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.vacationrequest.example.console.02.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      
      After task completion, the manager will find a new verification task in his task list.
      He can now accept or reject the vacation request, based on the input of the employee.
     <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.vacationrequest.example.console.03.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
     
     Since the database schema remains unchanged when we added BPMN 2.0 on top of the jBPM PVM, all
     existing reports can be applied to our new BPMN 2.0 processes.
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/bpmn2.vacationrequest.example.console.04.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
</chapter>
