<chapter id="delegationclasses">
  <title>Delegation classes</title>
  
   <section>
     <title>What are delegation classes</title>
     <para>Delegation classes are the classes that implement 
     <literal>Activity</literal> or <literal>Condition</literal>.  From the Process 
     Virtual Machine's perspective, these are external classes that provide 
     programming logic that is inserted into the PVM's graph execution.
     Delegation classes can be provided by the process languages as well 
     as by the end users.
     </para>
   </section>

   <section>
     <title>Configuration of delegation classes</title>
     <para>Delegation classes can be made configurable.  Member fields can 
     contain configuration parameters so that a delegation class can be 
     configured differently each time it is used.  For example, in the 
     <literal><link linkend="activity">Display</link></literal> activity,
     the message that is to be printed to the console is a configuration 
     parameter.
     </para>
     <para>Delegation classes should be stateless.  This means that executing the interface 
     methods should not change values of the member fields.  Changing member field values 
     of delegation classes during execution methods is actually changing the process 
     while it's executing.  That is not threadsafe and usually leads to unexpected 
     results.  As an exception, getters and setters might be made available to inject 
     the configuration cause they are used before the delegation object is actually 
     used in the process execution.
     </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Object references</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </section>
  
   <section>
     <title>Design time versus runtime</title>
     <para>TODO: the activity behaviour allows for design time as well as runtime behaviour.</para>
   </section>
    
   <section>
     <title>UserCodeInterceptor</title>
     <para>TODO: UserCodeInterceptor</para>
   </section>
    
   <section>
     <title>Member field configurations versus properties</title>
     <para>TODO: document field configurations versus properties</para>
   </section>
</chapter>