<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="signavio">
  
  <title>Signavio web modeler</title>
  
  <section id="signavioIntroduction">
    
    <title>Introduction</title>
    
    <para>Since version 4.1, jBPM ships with a completely open-source web-based BPMN 
    modeling tool called 'Signavio'. This Signavio web modeler is the result
    of a close collaboration between the JBoss jBPM team, 
    <ulink url="http://www.signavio.com/en.html">the company also named 'Signavio'</ulink>
    and the Hasso Plattner Instut (HPI) in Germany. Signavio is based on the 
    web-based modeling tool <ulink url="http://bpt.hpi.uni-potsdam.de/Oryx">
    Oryx</ulink>, which was developed in open-source by HPI. Both HPI and
    Signavio have comitted themselves to continue investing in Oryx and Signavio.
    More information about the initiative can be found 
    <ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/signavio-oryx-initiative/">here</ulink>.</para>
    
    <para>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/signavio.screenshot.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </para>
    
    <para>
    Using the Signavio web-based BPMN modeler, it is possible to let business 
    analyst model the business processes through their browser. The file format
    which is used to store the BPMN processes is actually jPDL. This means that
    the resulting processes can directly be imported into the Eclipse GPD and vice-versa. The process
    files will be stored on the hard disk, in 
    <literal>$jbpm_home/signavio-repository</literal> if you've used the default
    installation scripts.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    NOTE: The web-based BPMN modeling tool which ships with jBPM is 100% open-source
    (MIT-licence). The company <ulink url="http://www.signavio.com/en.html">Signavio</ulink>
    also offers commercial versions of the same modeling tool, enhanced with additional 
    features. Do note that new features, beneficial for the jBPM project, always
    will be comitted in the open-source repository of the modeling tool.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
    <section id="signavioInstallation">
    
    <title>Installation</title>
    
    <para>
    There are several ways of installing Signavio into your web container:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
      Use the demo.setup.jboss/tomcat scripts in <literal>$jbpm_home/install</literal>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      Use the install.signavio.into.jboss/tomcat scripts in <literal>$jbpm_home/install</literal>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      Copy the <literal>$jbpm_home/install/src/signavio/jbpmeditor.war</literal> 
      to your web container
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="signavioConfiguration">
    
    <title>Configuration</title>
    
    <para>
    Most of the Signavio configuration parameters can be changed in the 
    <literal>web.xml</literal> file, which you can find in <literal>jbpmeditor.war/WEB-INF/</literal>.
    The only parameters which is of real importance is the <literal>fileSystemRootDirectory</literal>
    parameter. The value of this parameter must point to an existing folder
    on your hard disk and indicates where the processes must be stored:
    <programlisting>
&lt;/context-param&gt;
  &lt;context-param&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;Filesystem directory that is used to store models&lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;param-name&gt;fileSystemRootDirectory&lt;/param-name&gt;&lt;param-value&gt;/home/jbarrez/dev/temp/jbpm-4.4-SNAPSHOT/signavio-repository&lt;/param-value&gt;
&lt;/context-param&gt;    
   </programlisting>
    </para>
    
    <para>
    If you use the installation scripts provided in <literal>$jbpm_home/install</literal>,
    this parameter is automatically set to <literal>$jbpm_home/signavio-repository</literal>
    during installation.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
</chapter>
